Finding Aid for Francis A. Allen papers, 1940-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Francis A. Allen papers 1940-2006
Allen, Francis A.
2.5 linear feet
0787 Aa2
Francis Allen was a professor at the University of Michigan Law School, from 1962 to 1986, and dean of the Law School, from 1966 to 1971. He also taught at Northwestern University, Harvard, the University of Chicago, and the University of Florida. He was chairman of the Attorney General's Commission on Poverty and the Administration of Federal Criminal Justice (1963), and took part in the psychosurgery court case Kaimowitz vs. Department of Mental Health for the State of Michigan, 1972-1979. Papers include a biography and bibliography, correspondence, published and unpublished works, court proceedings of the psychosurgery trial, speeches, other court documents, as well as sample examinations from his various law school courses.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Collection received in two accessions: first accession received through Francis Allen in 2000 (donor no. 8939 ), second accession received through June Allen in 2008.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Francis Alfred Allen was born in Kansas City, Kansas, in 1919. After attending Cornell College in Iowa, he served in the United States Army Air Corps as a weatherman during World War II. After the war, he continued on to Northwestern University to finish his law degree in 1946. He married June Walsh in 1947, and had two children, Neil and Susan.
Allen started his teaching career at Northwestern University in 1948. He subsequently went on to teach at Harvard (1953-1956) the University of Chicago (1956-1962 and 1963-1966), and the University of Michigan (1962-1963 and 1966-1986). He became dean of the Law School at the University of Michigan from 1966 to 1971.
Allen also participated in court proceedings throughout his career. After returning from World War II, Allen served as clerk to Chief Justice Fred Vinson from 1946 to 1948. In the early 1950s, he also served as a lawyer for a short time in the Cook County criminal court in Illinois. From 1972 to 1979, he took part in Kaimowitz vs. Department of Mental Health for the State of Michigan, in which patients of a mental institution felt that they were forced against their will to participate in psychosurgical procedures because of their status in society.
Allen concentrated most of his professional efforts towards reforming criminal law in the United States, as well as analyzing the concept of rehabilitation and how it has evolved over time. He also wrote and published many works on family law and juvenile law.
Because of his role as a reformer in the field of criminal law, Allen was often called to public service. In 1961, Allen played a pivotal role in the creation of the Illinois Criminal Code. But his most important accomplishment was the chairmanship of the Attorney General's Commission on Poverty and the Administration of Federal Criminal Justice. The report of that committee directly led to the passing of the Criminal Justice Act of 1964 and the Bail Reform Act of 1966.
Allen was also the recipient of many awards during his lifetime. In 1975, he was elected to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, and became President of the Association of American Law Schools in 1976. Allen was a visiting expert for the Salzburg Seminar of American Studies, and a scholar in residence at the Rockefeller Foundation in Bellagio, Italy. He also was a visiting professor for Northwestern University, Boston College, and the University of Chicago.
After retiring from the University of Michigan in 1986, Allen moved to Gainesville, Florida, were he taught at the University of Florida until his retirement in 1994. He passed away on April 6, 2007. He was survived by his wife June and son Neil.
The Francis A. Allen Papers are composed of professional and personal documents spanning 1940-2006, with the majority of the documents dating between 1950-2000. The bulk of the papers (roughly 50 percent) are correspondence, including professional, academic, and personal documents. The next biggest sub-set is a sampling of some of his published works as well as unpublished works. There are also documents from court cases he was involved in, speeches he delivered over the course of his career, and samples of student examinations he gave while teaching as a law school professor.
Subjects:
Allen, Francis A.; Law.; University of Michigan--Law School.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Psychosurgery.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series contains two folders. One contains a bibliography of Allen's published works from 1941 to 1998 as well as a résumé from 1997. The other folder contains two short biographies (an obituary from the Chicago Tribune, and one written upon Allen being named the Edson R. Sunderland Professor of Law Emeritus at the University of Michigan.)
  - Biographies (Box 1)
  - Bibliography (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1940-2006
  The Correspondence series, 1.5 linear feet, is arranged in alphabetical order. The types of correspondence range from personal letters, letters of recommendation, opinions on law matters or academia, and personal or financial business letters. For subjects (either individuals or institutions) with a large amount of correspondence, their materials were separated out into individual folders. Examples of these subjects include Allen's brother William, his brother Clark, various departmental units at the University of Michigan (the Law School, University Press, etc.), his close friend and colleague Norval Morris, and personal correspondence. Allen indicates on the upper right hand of most correspondence pages the name of the individual that the document pertains to, but his schema of doing this is at times inconsistent. Although the majority of the papers are organized by last name, sometimes they will be organized by the organization he was writing to instead of the individual to whom the letter was actually addressed (examples being the Harvard Law Review or the University of Chicago Press). In these cases the Harvard Law Review correspondence would be placed in the "H" folder, and the University of Chicago correspondence in the "C" folder. When there was a large number of documents pertaining to one individual or unit, care was taken to place the documents in reverse chronological order (in most cases, this was the original order that Allen used).
  The personal correspondence folder includes information regarding the publishing of Allen's works from various university presses (fax receipts, contracts, etc.), any documents containing Allen's social security number, and letters and cards of a personal nature. Although documents of this kind are also in other correspondence folders, the respect of the original order has been maintained.
  Common correspondents include:
  Allen’s family: Clark Allen and William Allen.
  Faculty colleagues at the University of Michigan: Lee C. Bollinger, Terrence Sandalow, Theodore St. Antoine, Thomas E. Sunderland, and Allan F. Smith.
  Colleagues at other law schools or professional organizations: Paul D. Carrington, Albert W. Alschuler, Dick Julin, Sanford Kadish, James Marsh, Norval Morris, Helen Silving, and Frank Zimring.
  Institutions:Harvard Law Review, departments within the University of Michigan (University Press, Administrative Affairs, Law School), Northwestern University, the Rockefeller Foundation, and the Salzburg Seminar.
  Others: Supreme Court Associate Justice Byron R. White, Walter O. Weyrauch, and Austin Wright.
  - A (Box 1)
  - Allen, Clark L. (Box 1)
  - Allen, Mark (Box 1)
  - Allen, Neil Walsh and Susan Lee 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Allen, William 1980-2001 (contains 1 color photograph) (Box 1)
  - Allen, William 1950-1978 (Box 1)
  - B (Box 1)
  - C (Box 1)
  - D (Box 1)
  - E (Box 1)
  - F-G (Box 1)
  - H-I (Box 1)
  - J (Box 1)
  - K (Box 1)
  - L (Box 1)
  - M (Box 1)
  - Michigan, University of (Box 1)
  - Morris, Norval 1950-2006 (Box 1)
  - Personal (Box 1)
  - N,P,Q (Box 1)
  - R (Box 2)
  - Sal-Sou (Box 2)
  - Sow-Syr (Box 2)
  - W (Box 2)
  - U-V (Box 2)
  - Y-Z (Box 2)
- Writings
  The Writings series contains a sampling of Allen's published works, dating from roughly 1950 to 2006, and comprises almost 0.5 linear feet. The majority of the works are book reviews, opinion articles, speeches and professional articles. Allen was published in many law review journals, newspapers, and magazines, and also wrote a few books. This series contains the Report of the Attorney General's Committee on Poverty and the Administration of Federal Criminal Justice, which was written in February 1963. Lastly, there is a folder of unpublished writings, which includes reactions to books, reports he was asked to write, and even poetry.
  - 1941-1949
    - "Confinement of the Sexually Irresponsible," 1941 (Box 2)
    - "Modernizing Illinois Eminent Domain Procedures," 1946 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "The Roosevelt Court: A Study in Judicial Politics and Values, 1937-1947" 1949 (Box 2)
  - 1950-1956
    - "The Wolf Case: Search and Seizure, Federalism, and the Civil Liberties," 1950 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "Melville Weston Fuller: Chief Justice of the United States, 1888-1910" 1950 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "Hold Your Tongue!," 1950 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "Cases on Criminal Law and Procedure," 1950 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "Russell on Crime," 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Due Process and State Criminal Procedures: Another Look," 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Chief Justice Vinson and the Theory of Constitutional Government: A Tentative Appraisal," 1954 (Box 2)
    - "Pioneers in Criminology, IV -- Raffaele Garfolo (1852-1934)," 1954 (Box 2)
    - "The Real Estate Transactions Seminar," 1955 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "International Lectures on Police Science," 1956 (Box 2)
    - "History, Empirical Research, and Law Reform: A Short Comment on a Large Subject," 1956 (Box 2)
    - "Law and the Future: Criminal Law and Administration," 1956 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "The Supreme Court in the American System of Government," 1956 (Box 2)
  - 1957-1959
    - Book Review: "Mens Rea in Statutory Offences," 1957 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "Not Guilty," 1957 (Box 2)
    - "Griffin vs. Illinois: Antecedents and Aftermath," 1957 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "Military Justice in the Armed Forces of the United States," 1957 (Box 2)
    - Review: "Report of the Committee on Homosexual Offences and Prostitution," 1957 (Box 2)
    - "The Borderland of the Criminal Law: Problems of 'Socializing' Criminal Justice," 1958 (Box 2)
    - "The Court and Civil Liberties," 1958 (Box 2)
    - "The Supreme Court and State Criminal Justice," 1958 (Box 2)
    - Draft copy: "Effective State Post-Conviction Procedures -- Their Nature and Essentialities," 1958 (Box 2)
    - "History, Empirical Research, and Law Reform: A Short Comment on a Large Subject," 1958 (Box 2)
    - Without footnotes: "The Supreme Court, Federalism, and State Systems of Criminal Justice," 1958 (Box 2)
    - With footnotes: "The Supreme Court, Federalism, and State Systems of Criminal Justice," 1958 (Box 2)
    - With footnotes: "Criminal Justice, Legal Values and the Rehabilitative Ideal," 1959 (Box 2)
    - "Memorial to Fred M. Merrifield," 1959 (Box 2)
    - Without footnotes: "Criminal Justice, Legal Values and the Rehabilitative Ideal," 1959 (Box 2)
  - 1960-1962
    - "A Look at Juvenile Court Procedures," 1960 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "Report of the Commission of Inquiry on Capital Punishment (Ceylon)," 1960 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "Wharton's Criminal Law and Procedure," 1960 (Box 2)
    - "The Right to Counsel: A Symposium," 1961 (Box 2)
    - "The Exclusionary Rule in the American Law of Search and Seizure," 1961 (Box 2)
    - "Federalism and the Fourth Amendment: A Requiem for Wolf," 1961 (Box 2)
    - "Offenses Against Property," 1962 (Box 2)
    - "The Rule of the American Law Institute's Model Penal Code," 1962 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "Procedure and Evidence in the Juvenile Court: A Guidebook for Judges," 1962 (Box 2)
  - February 1963
    - "Report of the Attorney General's Committee on Poverty and the Administration of Federal Criminal Justice," 1963 (Box 2)
    - Co-author: "Comments on 'Approaches to Court Imposed Compromise -- The Uses of Doubt and Reason'," 1964 (Box 2)
    - "Reflections on Hanging," 1964 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "Justice Holmes on Legal History," 1964 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "Mr. Justice Holmes and the Criminal Law," 1964 (Box 2)
    - "Ernst Freund: Scholar and Gentleman," 1965 (Box 2)
    - "Ernst Freund and the New Age of Legislation," 1965 (Box 2)
    - "Current Tendencies in American Narcotics Legislation," 1965 (Box 2)
    - "The Juvenile Court and the Limits of Juvenile Justice," 1965 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "Crime, Law, and Society," 1966 (Box 2)
    - "Civil Disobedience and the Legal Order," 1967 (Box 2)
  - 1968-1969
    - "Justice, Decency Are Indispensable," 1968 (Box 2)
    - "Liberty and Order," 1968 (Box 2)
    - "Legal Values and Correctional Values," 1968 (Box 2)
    - "One Aspect of the Problem of Relevance in Legal Education," 1968 (Box 2)
    - "Violence and the Law," 1969 (Box 2)
    - "'Law and Order' On What Terms?," 1969 (Box 2)
    - "Rights in Conflict: A Balanced Approach," 1969 (Box 2)
  - Circa 1960s (Date Unknown)
    - "The Supreme Court Discovers the Juvenile Court," ca. late 1960s-early 1970s (Box 2)
    - "Les Infractions Contre La Propriété," ca. late 1950s-early 1960s (Box 2)
    - "The Challenge of the Impoverished Accused in the Administration of Criminal Justice," ca. mid-1960s (Box 2)
  - 1970-1975
    - "Law Schools: Time of Troubles," 1970 (Box 2)
    - "Politics and the University," 1970 (Box 2)
    - "Issues Confronting the University," 1971 (Box 2)
    - "Freedom, Order and Justice," 1971 (Box 2)
    - "Mr. Justice Holmes and 'The Life of the Mind'," 1972 (Box 2)
    - "The Judicial Quest for Penal Justice: The Warren Court and the Criminal Cases," 1975 (Box 2)
    - "Foreword -- Quiescence and Ferment: The 1974 Term in The Supreme Court," 1975 (Box 2)
  - 1976-1979
    - "The Causes of Popular Dissatisfaction with Legal Education," 1976 (Box 2)
    - "The Criminal Law as an Instrument of Economic Regulation," 1976 (Box 2)
    - "Message From The President (Number 76-1)," 1976 (Box 2)
    - "Message From The President (Number 76-2)," 1976 (Box 2)
    - "President's Message for the September AALS Newsletter," 1976 (Box 2)
    - "Message From The President (Number 76-4)," 1976 (Box 2)
    - "The Causes of Popular Dissatisfaction with Legal Education," 1977 (Box 2)
    - "The Prospects of University Law Training," 1977 (Box 2)
    - "Criminal Law and the Modern Consciousness: Some Observations on Blameworthiness," 1977 (Box 2)
    - "The New Anti-Intellectualism In American Legal Education," 1977 (Box 2)
    - "Introduction [recognizing Helen Silving]," 1977 (Box 2)
    - "Untitled (recognizing Walter Schaefer)," 1979 (Box 2)
    - "On Winning and Losing," ca. late 1970s (Box 2)
    - "Resolving The Tension Between Professors and Practitioners," ca. late 1970s (Box 2)
    - "Bringing Substance Into A Formless Future," ca. late 1970s (Box 2)
  - 1981-1986
    - "The Morality of Means: Three Problems in Criminal Sanctions," 1981 (Box 2)
    - "Majorities, Minorities, and Morals: Penal Policy and Consensual Behavior," 1982 (Box 2)
    - "Ernst Freund," 1983 (Box 2)
    - "1984 -- The End Of Intimacy," circa 1983 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "American Law," 1984 (Box 2)
    - "A Serendipitous Trek Through the Advance-Sheet Jungle: Criminal Justice in the Courts of Review," 1985 (Box 2)
    - "Never Leaving Law School," 1986 (Box 2)
  - 1987-1989
    - "Commentary on Baldwin," 1987 (Box 2)
    - "The Erosion of Legality in American Criminal Justice: Some Latter-Day Adventures of the Nulla Poena Principle," 1987 (Box 2)
    - "What Provisions Should Govern Deans' Tenure?," 1988 (Box 2)
    - "Criminal Sentencing in the United States: A Survey in Aid of Comparative Study," 1988 (Box 2)
    - "Barriers To Excellence-A critical evaluation of UF's future," 1989 (Box 2)
    - "Remembering Shelley v. Kraemer: Of Public And Private Worlds," 1989 (Box 2)
    - "The Dolphin and the Peasant: Ill-Tempered, but Brief, Comments on Legal Scholarship," ca. late 1980s (Box 2)
  - 1990-1998
    - "The Dolphin and the Peasant: Ill-Tempered, but Brief, Comments on Legal Scholarship," 1990 (Box 2)
    - "On Coming Of Age: Twenty-Five Years Of The University Of Michigan Journal Of Law Reform," 1991 (Box 2)
    - "Joseph Richard Julin," 1993 (Box 2)
    - "1996 Fellows Research Award -- Yale Kamisar," 1996 (Box 2)
    - "The Scholarship Of Kenneth Pye," 1996 (Box 2)
    - Book Review: "The Poignant Paradoxes of Criminal Justice: A Review (reviewing Romantic Outlaws, Beloved Persons by Martha Grace Duncan)," 1996 (Box 2)
    - "The Comparative Study of Legal Institutions: The Case of American Criminal Justice," 1998 (Box 2)
  - 2000-2001
    - Book Review: "Stewards of Democracy: Law as a Public Profession," 2000 (Box 2)
    - "A Matter of Proportion," 2001 (Box 2)
  - Unknown Year/Journal
    - "Foreword" (written for a book by Frank Zimring) (Box 2)
    - "Foreword -- The Changing Borders of Juvenile Justice: Transfer of Adolescents to the Criminal Court" (Box 2)
  - Unpublished Writings (1940s 1956 1988)
    - Book Reviews: "Political Prisoners in American" and "The Seamy Side of Democracy," (year unknown) (Box 2)
    - "Untitled (handwritten poem, author unknown)," 1945 (Box 2)
    - "Some Observations on Legal Education; or a Law Student Speaks Out of Turn," 1942 (Box 2)
    - "Some Observations on 'Intellectual History' upon Reading Gabriel's Course of American Democratic Thought," 1944-45 (Box 2)
    - "Untitled (remarks about wartime reading)," 1946 (Box 2)
    - "Untitled (speech for the Illinois Sex Offense Commission)," ca. late 1940s (Box 2)
    - "Lines to K.L. and to Any Others Who May Be Interested" or "Dreams of Empire Vindicated," 1956 (Box 2)
    - "Legality," 1988 (Box 2)
- Psychosurgery Trial
  The Psychosurgery Trial series is three folders containing a variety of court documents, including pre-trial statements, opinions, affidavits, hearing notices, briefs, and papers that were collected prior to the litigation process. The timeline for the entire case spans from 1972 to 1979, although many of the documents are dated between 1972 and 1974, with only a few documents from the later years. The documents are in approximate chronological order, with the papers from the same year being grouped together, although not necessarily in correct monthly order. The documents in this series cover two trials, Kaimowitz vs. Department of Mental Health for the State of Michigan, and People of the State of Michigan vs. Louis Maurice Smith. Gabe Kaimowitz, on behalf of the Medical Committee for Human Rights and the Medical Care Division of the Michigan Public Health Association, represented the mistreated patients of the Michigan State Hospital System. Louis Maurice Smith was one of those patients, although his name had been changed to John Doe on many of the court documents. Allen was Smith's attorney during part of the trial.
  In the later years of the People vs. Smith trial (1978-1979), it eventually reached the Michigan Supreme Court. Although these documents are fewer in number, they provide a concise timeline of the entire psychosurgery trial since 1972.
  - General (1) 1972-1976 (Box 3)
  - General (2) 1973 (Box 3)
  - General (3) 1972-1979 (Box 3)
- Speeches
  The Speeches series is separated into folders according to year, which are in reverse chronological order. The dates of Allen's speeches range from 1952 to 1988. The types of speeches include addresses to various law schools, professional organizations, and political organizations, speeches where he gives his opinion on a legal subject, those given as Dean of the Law School at the University of Michigan, memorial services, presentations, and lectures. A great many of them are dedicated to the controversies of legal action during the Vietnam War.
  - 1980-1991 Unknown Year (Box 3)
  - 1970-1978 (Box 3)
  - 1961-1968 (Box 3)
  - 1952-1959 (Box 3)
- Student Examinations
  The Student Examinations series consists of two folders: one of exams given at the University of Michigan, and the other of exams given at all other schools where Allen taught, including Northwestern, Harvard, the University of Chicago, and the University of Florida. The dating for this series ranges from roughly 1950 to the 1990s. In some cases, Allen had written out by hand answers to some of the exams. If those answers were found to match one of the exams, the answer sheets were placed immediately after the exam.
  - University of Michigan, 1984-85 (Box 3)
  - Non-University of Michigan schools 1950s-1994 (Box 3)
- Trial Proceedings
  The Trial Proceedings series covers two time periods where Allen participated in court cases. One is a group of moot court cases that were conducted while Allen attended Northwestern University from 1940 to 1941. The other is a group of actual court cases conducted in Cook County, Illinois, and the Supreme Court of Illinois, from 1951 to 1953.
  - 1951-1953 (Box 3)
  - 1940-1941 (Northwestern University moot trials) (Box 3)